hello I'm Korra chistosa welcome to a
new program from Washington on today
show the cracking of whistleblowers by
the US government our guest John
Kiriakou a whistleblower and former CIA
analyst mr. kyriacou warm welcome to the
program thank you for having me John you
have said and I read and I quote your
words my case was never about leaking my
case was about blowing the whistle on
torture and you have said torture is
wrong under any circumstance what
happened to you I I was talking to a
reporter for ABC News the reporter told
me he was writing a book on the CIA's
rendition detention and interrogation
program that's the program where the CIA
will will kidnap or snatch a person that
they believe to be a member of a
terrorist group and send him either to
Guantanamo or to a third country I told
him I didn't know anybody who was
involved in renditions it just wasn't my
area so he sent me a list of names and
he said can you introduce me to any of
these people I said I couldn't he did
this a second time finally he said what
about the man that you mentioned in your
book that you ran into in Pakistan and I
said oh that's I'm going to use the name
that's John Doe I said I don't know what
ever happened to him he's probably
retired that was a crime that was a
felony and the government prosecuted me
because you were the one who really was
really blowing the whistle about
waterboarding and and this is exactly my
point what I what I did really isn't a
crime that happens every day in
Washington if you read The Washington
Post to the new york times you see CIA
people quoted all the time or the names
of CIA people but the fact of the matter
is that in december of 2007 i went on
national television and i said three
things i said the CIA is torturing its
prisoners I said that torture is
official US government policy and I said
that the
himself had approved of that policy they
started investigating me within 24 hours
the investigation never ended and
finally four years later they charged me
with five felonies and then you end up
in jail and you were serving at 23
months sentence in jail yes then a house
arrest and you officially you are in
supervised release sort of probation
career still today I still am I actually
am until the middle of 2018 I'm
considered to be a criminal and so if I
want to leave the Washington area I have
to have written permission at least one
week in advance and if i want to go
overseas I have to get written
permission from my judge one month in
advance and then there's petty
harassment crossing the borders and each
time I say to these border these border
agents you can't stop me from coming
into my own country you may want to you
may try to but you can't stop me from
coming into my so you ended up in
gym for attending the truth yeah I I
said that we were torturing these people
that torture was wrong it was wrong
under any circumstances and I also said
that despite what the Bush
administration Justice Department said
torture is a violation of both US law
and international law and I'll tell you
something in January of 1968 The
Washington Post ran a photograph of an
American soldier waterboarding a North
Vietnamese prisoner when that photograph
was published the Defense Department
initiated an investigation and that
soldier was put on trial and he was
convicted of torture and he was
imprisoned so if waterboarding was
torture in 1968 why was it not torture
in 2002 the law never changed and indeed
the United States is a signatory to many
international conventions and treaties
that ban torture in many of those cases
we wrote those international conventions
and treaties so we're telling other
countries don't torture torture is
illegal but they
we torture and it's okay for us talk
about the torture that were practice and
you correct me something is missing or
wrong waterboarding sexual abuse with
broomsticks rectal feeding rectal
hydration with Hamas power drills making
awful noises sleep deprivation up to 180
hours in one case hands shuckle above
the heads and all those people who
practice that torture are not in jail
you were the only ones who ended up in
jail I was the only one who ended up in
jail and i will add something to that
list and this is something that we now
know from the Senate torture report and
from the CIA inspector general's report
and that was what they called the cold
cell they they strip a prisoner naked
they chained him to an eyebolt in the
ceiling and they chill the cell to 50
degrees Fahrenheit and then every hour
they throw ice water on him now we
murdered a prisoner in that way in fact
there was an article in Newsweek in one
of the recent issues of Newsweek
magazine saying that this CIA officer
who murdered the prisoner using the cold
cell retired at full pension and is now
teaching at a university at a Catholic
University no less the former Virginia
congressman his name is Jim Moran now
retired has said in the Congress that
that you deserve a presidential pardon
and he didn't get it but you thinking
you are thinking eventually to request
one to write the letter to the president
eventually next year I think I would
like to ask next year for the president
to pardon me my my thought is I have a
great deal of political support not just
on the left but on the right to people
like John McCain for example on the
political right who are opposed to
torture and so because being tortured
and he has and he is the only member of
Congress who has actually been tortured
so if anybody in Congress is an
authority on the
of torture it's Senator John McCain you
can disagree with his political
positions on other issues but nobody
knows torture like John McCain does so I
I have a measure of hope that in the
final days of President Obama's
administration that he may think kindly
enough on me that he might issue a
pardon if he doesn't the law allows me
to apply for a pardon every two years
and maybe the next president will decide
to part eventual if it's a Democrat
because of its a rebellious Republican I
have no chance you have already
mentioned that president bush and in
2007 he said categorically we do not
torture prisoners yes and you said that
you knew that was a lie it was a lie you
use a word lie and then you say the
whole torture program talking about the
US was approved by President Bush
himself and was a very planned program
so there's no room for for discussion no
there's no room for discussion or
interpretation the president was lying
he was lying to the American people in
order to cover up this torture program I
remember briefing the deputy director of
the CIA which is something that I did
every morning for a year in in my last
year with the organization and I
remember that the president's memo had
just arrived in which he authorized the
torture program and I remember the
deputy director just repeating over and
over I can't believe he signed that memo
it was as though they said well let's
ask him if we can torture he'll probably
say no but at least we should ask well
we asked and he said yes and even at the
CIA at the top levels of the CIA they
couldn't believe he said yes and not
only the if you want international laws
being violated but one of the issues
here is that the torturing is not giving
any results now see this is you're
exactly right this is one of the things
that that most Americans either don't
know or don't understand and it's that
torture never works
we know from both the Senate torture
report and the CIA inspector general's
report that no actionable intelligence
was collected through the use of torture
and we know that no American lives were
saved through the use of torture when
people are being tortured they'll tell
their their interrogator anything that
they think that person wants to hear
just to make the torture stop even if
they give correct information they give
so much incorrect information that you
can't you can't call through the
information you can't you can't analyze
it quickly enough to decide what's true
and what's not true so none of it ends
up being in the case of Vice President
Dick Cheney he was really pushing and
saying openly that he will do it again
and he doesn't repent and he believes
that that's a way that was was very
positive the results that we got and you
have said being asked should he be tried
and you say yes yes I think that dick
cheney is a war criminal I think that he
intentionally violated international law
he violated international human rights
and he ought to be punished for his
crimes the thing about dictating Dick
Cheney as well is that he is completely
unrepentant he makes no apologies for
what he did and says that he would do it
again there has to be a country out
there whether it's germany or spain or
someone who's willing to file criminal
charges against him and i know that
he'll never be arrested certainly and
he'll never be tried for a crime but
someone ought to make it official and
someone ought to charge him it we just
haven't seen that kind of courage yet
what about President George Bush well I
think George Bush also should be should
be charged with crimes against humanity
as should George Tenet the the leader of
the CIA as should Donald Rumsfeld the
former Secretary of Defense see and the
reason why so many of these people who
were involved in the torture program
have really gone all in and and they
still say it was right it was good it
was successful is because this is their
legacy when they die and their
obituaries are written it's going to say
that they were the leaders of the
torture program so dr. regimes you may
even mention a torture regime and for
the rest of their lives they're going to
try to convince the American people that
this was the right thing to do and that
it worked would you put your hand on the
fire that today today the u.s. is not
torturing I like to think that the u.s.
is not but you wouldn't put your hand I
would not bet money I would not put my
hand no and going to the subject of
whistleblowers you have said that Edward
Snowden is a national hero why because
Edward Snowden knew what he was getting
into and yet still took the risk to tell
the American people that their
government is spying on them it was
illegal when I was working for the CIA
it was illegal to collect information on
an American citizen if NSA even
accidentally initials I'm sorry if the
National Security Agency accidentally
collected information on an American
citizen or collected a phone call from
an American citizen they would have to
delete it from their systems and then
they would have to inform Congress that
they had accidentally intercepted an
American well now they intercept every
American's phone calls emails text
messages and they have enough storage
space in their new facility in in the
state of Utah to save it for 500 years
and on top of that address accusation is
internationally also they are gathering
information there's not a country on
Earth that isn't vulnerable to having
their personal information collected by
the National Security Administration and
the CIA the candidate Bernie Sanders
Democratic presidential candidate ben
Dyson's said regarding Edward Snowden
and I quote I think Snowden play a very
important role in educating the American
people to the
in which our civil liberties and our
constitutional rights are being
undermined you agree I do agree and I
think Bernie Sanders is one of only
probably two people running for
president who has the courage to say
something like that I agree with Bernie
Sanders position on Eddie stone I think
he did a great national service and if
it wasn't for ed Snowden we wouldn't
have any idea what our own government
was doing to us you were mentioning that
Obama administration is really cracking
down very very hard on whistleblowers we
as we had had the opportunity to
interview Julian Assange inside the
embassy of Ecuador in London first
interview after three months only three
months after he has getting diplomatic
asylum now it's already three years yes
and Joe Biden the vice president of the
United States has said that Julian
Assange is a cyber-terrorist you know
Joe Biden used to be the voice of reason
I was convicted of violating a law
called the intelligence identities
Protection Act of nineteen eighty two
not only did Joe Biden vote against that
law but he wrote an op-ed in the
Christian Science Monitor saying that
that law was unconstitutional and it
caused a chilling effect on our freedom
of speech now today the obama-biden
administration has prosecuted not just
me but eight other whistleblowers under
the Espionage Act the Espionage Act was
written in 1917 to target German
saboteurs during the First World War
from 1917 until 2009 it was used three
times in American history since barack
obama was elected president nine people
have been charged under the Espionage
Act have none of us i should say have
been accused of of giving information to
a foreign government or foreign power of
any kind we've all been accused of
blowing the whistle on waste fraud abuse
and illegality where is the US acting
like that leaving the word democracy as
a way to conduct the life
the u.s. is really a democracy because
if I realize that for telling the truth
you could end up in jail as you did
Edward Snowden end up in Russia is
Julian essential three years inside the
embassy of Ecuador it's a way of
creating terror you could be terrorized
to tell the truth so it's a way to
practice terrorism or not I I gave a
radio interview recently and a woman
called with a question when she said if
you know that they're targeting you you
know that they're listening to you you
know that they're following you in fact
they even sent you to prison she said
why are you still speaking out why are
you still talking she said I would be
completely silent terrorized terrorized
that's the definition of terrorism and I
said the founding fathers of the United
States gave me a constitutional right to
freedom of speech and I intend to
exercise that right just as those
founding fathers intended I said Barack
Obama will not silence me george w bush
will not silence me I have a right and I
intend to use it so you you do not
repent of you have done absolutely not I
Oh as crazy as it might sound I would do
the whole thing again why crazy someone
has to stand up and tell these these
people that enough is enough that what
they're doing is wrong we have problems
with civil rights we have problems with
human rights we have problems with civil
liberties and we're using the most
draconian aunty spying law to crackdown
on whistleblowers this is not this is
not the kind of government that I want
jesselyn Radack who is one of my
attorneys and who is a whistleblower
herself says I want my September 10th
country back and that's exactly how I
feel so in reality it is hypocrisy and
even to be perverse that you guys that
are really feeling patriotic because you
really want to stay
to the principles of the founding
fathers yes are trying to be portrayed
as the unpatriotic yes the traitors
which is exactly the opposite day real
the real ones that could be accused is
the other part is the other side in fact
the day after I I went on ABC News and I
said we were torturing prisoners a
sitting u.s. senator said that I should
be charged with treason which is a
death-penalty charge and a woman who
works at one of the conservative
Republican think tanks wrote an op-ed in
the San Francisco Chronicle saying that
I should be put to death for the
revelations that I made that energized
me even more and I'll tell you another
thing too about this administration for
the first time in American history we're
murdering American citizens overseas
with the use of drones these are
Americans who have not been given their
constitutional right to face their
accusers in court they have not been
charged with any crime for example if
unmarked was a Yemeni American Muslim
Imam if if he was the terrorist that the
government wants us to think he was why
didn't they charge him with a crime why
did they just murder him and then a week
later they murdered his 16 year old son
for good measure sitting at a cafe and
murdered the cousin who happened to be
having tea collateral damage collateral
damage never issued an apology we have
kidnapped a Canadian professor muharram
kidnapped him from a plane at John F
Kennedy Airport in New York and sent him
to Syria to be tortured never apologized
when they determined he was the wrong
guy we kidnapped a German citizen named
khalid al masah tea and sent him first
to Afghanistan and then to Egypt to be
tortured and then realized he was the
wrong guy we never issued an apology
I mean this is the government that that
we have now when did this happen how did
this happen and that's why I want my
September 10th country back I mean that
sense why the population is not reacting
as you do with with moral principle I
think the population in general believes
the propaganda that both the Bush and
Obama administrations have fed the
American people saying we have to do
this this is the only way to keep the
country safe you know I heard I heard
somebody say just recently on the news
that yes that these tactics are very
hard but we haven't been attacked since
September 11th so it works but let me
interrupt you there because if you say I
heard them in the news but if you dig a
little bit deeper only six corporations
own ninety percent of the media examined
those corporations in a way control
ninety percent of the agenda of
information that fits almost three
hundred millions America so in reality
the question is is the news media
independent is it you mean news media
informing or is misinforming purposely
ya iya I will admit to you that that in
prison I stopped watching the news the
mainstream news why because I don't
believe them for the very reason that
you mentioned the American news is a
corporate owned entity and I'll give you
an example the intercept reported
recently owned by Greenwald then it has
been part of the documentary who owned
that's right the Academy Award for
Edward Snowden Arab citizen for so the
intercept reported on based on leaked
documents related to the drone program
they said this is the kill list this is
how people find themselves on the kill
list this is how the president decides
who to kill that news appeared in the
intercept and on the Huffington Post
which is owned by Arianna Huffington it
appeared nowhere else
it didn't appear in the New York Times
The Wall Street Journal the Washington
posed and news network the news networks
finally a couple of days later CNN had a
very small story but there really hasn't
been anything out there and it's because
large corporations which which have you
know a vested interest in maintaining
the status quo don't want us to know
these kinds of things so I find myself
watching foreign news channels and and
reading the Alternative Press I now I
get my news from Twitter if you if you
rewind and you say well and I was a very
successful CIA basically analyst and
your life has been ruined because of
that yes my life has been ruined I can't
find a decent job no company will ever
employ me again I lost my house at least
temporarily I hope to move back into it
sometime next year I had to sell all of
my possessions to pay my attorneys the
government took my pension my federal
pension after almost 20 years of
government service and i still owe my my
lawyers eight hundred and eighty
thousand dollars for Sam even though
almost a million dollars I actually
spent more than a million dollars and
they they cut the bill a little bit how
I'm going to repay that I don't have any
idea but you're well with yourself
because you are defending your
principles the principles of that you
believe that your country are based on
yes that's right I can sleep at night my
children are proud of me my wife is
proud of me and I know in my heart I did
the right thing John Kiriakou thank you
very much for joining us thanks for
having me